[Music]
we've previously explored the issue of
lead contamination in calcium
supplements like bone meal but it wasn't
just bone meal and substantial
quantities of lead were found in other
more common over-the-counter supplements
still testing revealed continued public
health concern over bone meal but
thankfully it's not as popular these
days so many of us are not likely to get
directly exposed to the lead in bone
meal anymore but may get indirectly
exposed to the animals we eat
in the u.s five billion pounds of meat
and bone meal are produced as
slaughterhouse byproducts every year
what do we do with these millions of
tons every year we feed it back to farm
animals particularly chickens
now most of the lead in the bone meal
passes right through the animals into
their waste but then we take that waves
to cow pig and chicken feces and feed it
back to the animals again you guessed it
so
you can see how the levels of
contaminants might build up in their
bodies
i've talked previously about what that
might mean for making something like
chicken soup but the original concern
about these kind of feeding practices of
feeding cows to cows and
pigs and chickens was the spread of
prion diseases like mad cow disease but
it's not just prions that this kind of
recycling can magnify but other toxic
substances including lead
so more plant-based dye may be able to
lower lead exposure and even more
plant-based diet could theoretically
lower exposure even more
but you've got to put it to the test but
should we expect to find a benefit and
yes lead is one of the toxins found in
meat
but half of our dietary exposure
probably comes from plant foods
dietary modeling studies in europe
suggest that vegetarians would be
exposed to about the same amount of lead
compared to the general population with
the exception of those who eat a lot of
wild game which can end up with a
thousand times more lead than most other
foods
in fact a vegetarian diet may even be
higher in lead
but it's not what you eat
it's what you absorb
as we learn from the cadmium story the
uptake of toxic heavy metals from animal
food sources into the human intestinal
lining cells may be higher than that
from vegetable sources
that's how you have a vegetarian with
some of the lowest concentrations of
lead and cadmium in their blood despite
higher concentrations in their diet
but you don't know
until you
put it to the test
there seemed to be a tendency towards
higher fecal elimination of lead
following change to a vegetarian diet
with nine subjects on average tripling
their elimination of lead three
unaffected and four dropping by about
half
but the study only lasted a few months
the difference wasn't statistically
significant so
let's try
a year
a shift towards a diet characterized by
large amounts of raw vegetables fruits
and unrefined foods whole grains
with the exclusion of meat poultry fish
and eggs though it did include fermented
dairy like a type of soured milk as well
as cutting back on processed food and
junk they took clippings of hair before
and after the shift and got significant
reductions in heavy metals including
cutting their lead level nearly in half
check this out
this is how much mercury cadmium and
lead they had oozing from their body
into their hair when they started
and within three months their toxic
heavy metals went down and stayed down
how do we know it wasn't just a
coincidence
because they went back up a few years
later after the study was over after
they went back to more of a regular diet
their mercury cadmium and lead levels
shot back up to where they were before
same thing with a different group after
two years the drop in mercury is easy to
explain presumably due to the drastic
drop in fish consumption and the drop in
alcoholic beverages may have contributed
to the drop in lead but
it could also have been a cadmium-like
effect where the decrease in hair lead
content could be due to the dietary
shift resulting in less absorption of
lead into the body in the first place
[Music]
so